Guide to the Eleanor Chase Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eleanor Chase papers
1914-1996
1914-1944
YCAL MSS 748
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.67
(9 boxes)
Chase, Eleanor, 1903-1944
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, writings, photographs, and scrapbooks documenting the life and literary career of Eleanor Chase. Correspondence contains incoming letters to Eleanor Chase (1919 to 1943). Principal correspondents include W. Graham Robertson and Robert Benchley. Also included is one letter to Alexandra Fatio Taylor from Helen Keller, 1953. Writings consist chiefly of typescript drafts of novels, short stories, poetry, and drama, most of which were unpublished during Chase's lifetime. Photographs include portraits of Eleanor Chase and of literary critic Alexander Woolcott. Scrapbooks, which have been disbound, contain letters, photographs, and clippings related to Eleanor Chase, her writings, and her family.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Alexandra Taylor on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2000. Gift of Alexandra Taylor, 2003-2007.
Eleanor Chase (1903-1944)
Eleanor Chase Fatio, American novelist and socialite, was born in Oshkosh, Wisconsin, on March 3, 1903 to Nia Sawyer and Charles Curry Chase. In 1928 she published her first novel, Pennagan Place (New York: J. H. Sears & Co.). Her second novel, The Last of Wisdom (New York: J. H. Sears & Co.) followed in 1932. Chase was a member of the Authors League and friend of Alexander Woolcott and Robert Benchley.
Eleanor Chase married the Swiss-born architect Maurice Fatio in 1929. The couple lived in New York and Palm Beach, Florida. She died on October 21, 1944 and was survived by her children, Alexandra Fatio Taylor and Maurice Pierre Fatio.
Additional biographical information can be found in Eleanor of Palm Beach, by Hubert Pryor ([Philadelphia, PA: Xlibris Corp., 2002).
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1919-1953. II. Writings, 1914-1944. III. Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1910-1996.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Scrapbooks; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Benchley, Robert, 1889-1945; Chase, Eleanor, 1903-1944; Fatio, Maurice, 1897-1943; Robertson, W. Graham; Woollcott, Alexander, 1887-1943
- Correspondence, 1919-1953; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence contains incoming letters to Eleanor Chase (1919 to 1943). Principal correspondents include W. Graham Robertson and Robert Benchley. Also included is one letter to Alexandra Fatio Taylor from Helen Keller, 1953.
  Additional correspondence may be found in Scrapbooks (Series III.).
  - Chase, Eleanor, 1919-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Taylor, Alexandra Fatio from Helen Keller, 1953 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1914-1944; Series II; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Writings contain the autograph manuscript and typescript drafts and clippings of novels, short stories, poetry, and plays written by Eleanor Chase. A play adaptation of Chase's novel Pennagan Place written by Warren B. Duff is also included.
  Additional writings may also be found in Scrapbooks listed below.
  Arrangement
  Organized into four subseries: Novels, Short Stories, Poetry, and Drama.
  - Novels
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "The Grove," bound typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "The Moon Had a Golden Ring," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
    - "The Moon Had a Golden Ring," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 13-18)
    - "Pennajam [sic] Place," chapter one, typescript draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Short Stories
    - "Aftermath," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Amends," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "At Thy Sweet Voice," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "A Black Hat for Aunt Harriet," co-written with George Oppenheimer, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Doris," autograph manuscript, 1924 December 7 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "The Editor Is Not Responsible," typescript drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "The Egoist," typescript drafts, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Enter Little Emily," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "Every Hyacinth the Garden Wears," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "The Fall of the House of Hawkes," typescript drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Habit," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Hide-Out," typescript drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "His Chum," in the Los Angeles Sunday Times, newspaper clipping, 1917 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "His Heart to Hold," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "I Miss an Attic," typescript, with related clipping, 1937; undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - "Making-Over Martie," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - "The Marquis Buys a Rug," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - "Miss Finger and the Ministers," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - "Mrs. Ulysses," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - "Night-Shift," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - "Nothing To Do With It," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - "Object Lessons for Little Girls," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "One of the Crowd," typescript drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - "One of the Signers," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - "Pennagan Interlude," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - "Recess," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - "Seconds," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - "Something To Do," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - "The Son of the King of England," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - "Sonny Temple and Timothy Tucker," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - "Thirty-Five," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - "Tivetson's Point of View," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - "Values," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - "Wedding Day," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Poems
    Organized under two headings: Collected Poetry and Poems.
    - Collected Poetry
      - "Across the Way & Other Poems," typescript, with clipping, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - "Arpeggio," autograph manuscript and typescript draft with clippings, 1917, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - "Heart Murmurs," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 56-57)
    - Poems
      - "Ah, even then bemused by grief...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - "America is waking...," and "A new dress....," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - "Anthony, Anthony...," "As every draft...," and "Autumn 1940...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - "The Canning Tower," newspaper clipping, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - "Conscience is my counsellor...," and "Do you remember...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - "Does it prove...," "England...," and "Egypt's fair...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - "Forever...," "God knows...," and "Go softly...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - "Have you finished...," "How sweet a thing...," and "Here with twilight...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - "He loses another...," and "I cannot say of you...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - "I don't know what...," and "If I have smiled...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - "If I should suddenly...," and "I ran down the highway...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - "I had a ship...," "I cannot keep...," and "I always love...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - "I love within...," "I would be if...," "I live by prayer...," and "I've never been...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - "Knowing I love you...," "My heart...," and "My happiness...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - "My grandmother...," "Oh, plant a rose...," and "O, I'll be glad...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - "Once I made a...," "One shouldn't let...," and "Only one thing...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - "Paris on a...," "Parts are written...," and "Poem to Mother," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - "Right way or wrong way...," "So let me love you...," and "Strange what simple...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - "So we lie...," and "So if I say...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - "Solitude without...," "Too many times...," "This is at once...," and "They were so...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - "They cannot love...," "The wind blew wet...," and "The wind and the child...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - "The train gives...," "The summer still...," "There is this...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - "There is no victory...," and "The colors of the world...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - "The morning dawned...," "The little leaves...," and "Trees in the spring...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - "Until the singing...," "Up the hill...," and "What if you had...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - "We shall not share...," "We might have loved...," and "We might mock...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
      - "Whatever gods are mine...," "What is life...," and "What strange obsession...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - "When I see the...," When this is gone...," and "Where shall we look...," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - Unsorted poems, autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 86-88)
  - Drama
    - "I Came to Tell of Love," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - "Marya," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - "Those Who Marry," by Warren B. Duff, adapted from the novel Pennagan Place by Eleanor Chase, typescript, annotated, undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Untitled play, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 92)
- Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1910-1996; Series III; 0.79; (4 boxes)
  Photographs and Scrapbooks contain black and white photographs of Eleanor Chase Fatio, literary critic Alexander Woolcott, and disbound scrapbooks containing letters, clippings and photographs relating to the life and family of Eleanor Chase Fatio.
  - Photographs
    - Chase, Eleanor, circa 1910-1937 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Chase, Eleanor and Maurice Pierre Fatio, black and white photograph, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Woolcott, Alexander, undated (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Unidentified photographs of a woman and a dog, black and white photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Oversize photographs, circa 1910-1937 (Box 7, Folder 97-98)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook containing photographs, letters, and writings [disbound], 1914-1942 (Box 8, Folder 99-103)
    - Scrapbook containing photographs, letters, and writings [disbound], 1934-1996 (Box 9, Folder 104-108)